Guide to the Brooklyn hospitals and health services organizations collection ARC.141
Brooklyn Historical Society
Brooklyn hospitals and health services organizations collection
1829-1997
1861-1939
Brooklyn Historical Society
Lutheran Hospital Association of the City of New York and Vicinity (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
ARC.141
3.1 Linear Feet in six manuscript boxes and two pamphlet boxes
The Brooklyn hospitals and health services organizations collection contains records of various Brooklyn hospitals and health services organizations, many of which were affiliated with charitable organizations or religious denominations and provided care to Brooklyn's disadvantaged and underserved citizenry.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Portions of this collection were the gift of St. Martha's Sanitarium and Dispensary, 1897; the House of St. Giles the Cripple, 1915; the Prospect Heights Hospital and Brooklyn Maternity, 1927; Sally Forbes, 2004; B.J. McAfee, date unknown; the Jeri Finesilver Screening Clinic, date unknown; and George W. Schiebler, date unknown. Sources and dates of acquisition for all remaining items in the collection are unknown.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged alphabetically by institution name.
Historical Note
In colonial New York, only a small number of almshouse infirmaries existed to care for the sick, while the mentally ill were usually imprisoned or placed in poorhouses. It was not until the early to mid-19th century, when the New York City area's dependent and poor population increased dramatically, that hospitals and other health services organizations, such as homeopaths and maternity wards, began to emerge. In Brooklyn specifically, the earliest hospitals included the Kings County Hospital, which grew out of an almshouse infirmary in 1831, and the Brooklyn City Hospital, which was incorporated in 1845. One of Brooklyn's first mental institutions was also established in Flatbush in 1845.
Most health services organizations that were established during this period were affiliated with charitable organizations, religious denominations, or ethnic groups, and had meager resources with which to care for patients. Hospitals, for instance, provided shelter, meals, and only minimal medical care, usually administered by poorly trained staff in unsanitary conditions, while mental health institutions suffered from extreme overcrowding. Because of the social stigma attached to such institutions, middle and upper class citizens usually received medical care in the privacy of their homes.
Popular attitudes toward public health institutions began to change in the late 19th and early 20th centuries. Advances in conventional medical science, aided by the professionalization of nursing, began to improve the quality of care offered by hospitals and other infirmaries. As affluent citizens were urged by their physicians to use the ever-improving medical facilities, the number of hospitals in New York City began to rise. In 1908, there were 63 general hospitals in New York, and by 1930 there were 125.
Likewise, the emergence of the mental hygiene movement also spurred an increase in the quality of care offered to New York's mentally ill, who were admitted to the Manhattan Psychiatric Center, the world's largest mental hospital, or were transferred to improved psychiatric wards at hospitals throughout New York State. By the 1930s, 25,000 New York City residents resided in state mental institutions. Homeopathic practice, too, had substained a substantial following between 1860 and 1900, with over 100 homeopathic institutions operating in the city at the turn of the 20th century.
Congruous to the improvement of the city's public health facilities in the late 19th and early 20th centuries was the increase in public awareness of social issues relevant to public health, such as sanitation, preventive practices, and temperance. Education on these issues was facilitated by a growing number of advocate groups and charities established by the city's affluent citizenry and religious denominations.
By the early 20th century, the widescale professionalization of medical practice in New York City had firmly taken root, though several significant alterations would continue to be made to the city's public health system throughout the 20th century.
Sources:
Cordasco, Francesco. "Homeopathy," in The Encyclopedia of New York City, ed. Kenneth T. Jackson (New Haven, Conn.: Yale University Press; New York: New York Historical Society, c1995), 554-555.
Opdycke, Sandra. "Mental Health," in The Encyclopedia of New York City, ed. Kenneth T. Jackson (New Haven, Conn.: Yale University Press; New York: New York Historical Society, c1995), 749-750.
Opdycke, Sandra, and David Rosner. "Hospitals," in The Encyclopedia of New York City, ed. Kenneth T. Jackson (New Haven, Conn.: Yale University Press; New York: New York Historical Society, c1995), 560-563.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
If digital surrogates exist, they should be used in place of the originals whenever possible.
Related Materials
Brooklyn Hospital records (ARC.225)
Lutheran Hospital of Brooklyn collection (2006.032)
Long Island College Hospital collection (ARC.139)
Photographs of St. Mary's Maternity Hospital (V1991.125)
Brooklyn Eye and Ear Hospital records (1985.005)
Methodist Episcopal Hospital reports and publications (ARC.155)
Viscount and Viscountess Halifax photographs of Jewish Hospital in Brooklyn (V1974.017)
Mortimer D. Jones collection on the Kings County Hospital (1994.008)
Norwegian Lutheran Deaconesses' Home and Hospital annual reports and receipts (ARC.246)
Long Island College Hospital School of Nursing Alumnae Association records (2014.006)
Medical Society of the County of Kings collection (1985.116)
Brooklyn Home for Consumptives Annual Report collection (1985.099)
City of Brooklyn, Department of Health vital statistics (ARC.160)
Visiting Nurse Association of Brooklyn records (1985.093)
Scope and Contents
The Brooklyn hospitals and health services organizations collection contains records of various Brooklyn hospitals and health services organizations, many of which were affiliated with charitable organizations or religious denominations and provided care to Brooklyn's disadvantaged and underserved citizenry.
Many types of institutions are represented in the collection, including general hospitals and dispensaries; women and children's hospitals; hospitals and dispensaries serving a specific religious denomination or ethnic group; specialized hospitals and dispensaries; mental institutions; terminal care facilities; rehabilitation centers; homeopathic hospitals and dispensaries; medical societies and preventive health organizations; and medical colleges and nurse training schools.
Materials in the collection consist mainly of annual reports and yearbooks containing essential summary information on an organization, including historical sketches; lists of board members, officers, and medical staff; constitutions, bylaws, and articles of incorporation; reports of various officers; financial statements; medical and surgical statistics and reports; lists of subscribers, members, and contributors; details regarding monetary donations; and rules for the admission of patients. While the annual reports and yearbooks do contain general information on individuals who received care from a particular organization, specific names are withheld.
Additional materials in the collection include constitutions and bylaws, rules of procedure, progress reports, medical manuals, catalogs, member and alumnae lists, newsletters and bulletins, brochures, and various ephemeral literature.
The following organizations are represented in the collection, listed by institution type:
General Hospitals and Dispensaries:
Bedford Dispensary and Hospital (also represented under its previous names, including the Bedford Dispensary Association and the Bedford Dispensary)
Bethany Deaconess Hospital Society
Brooklyn Central Dispensary
Brooklyn City Dispensary
Brooklyn Eclectic Dispensary
Brooklyn State Hospital (also represented under its previous name, the Long Island State Hospital)
Bushwick Hospital
People's Medical and Surgical Dispensary
Prospect Heights Hospital (also represented under its previous names, including the Brooklyn Homeopathic Lying-In Asylum; the Brooklyn Homeopathic Maternity; the Brooklyn Maternity; and the Prospect Heights Hospital and Brooklyn Maternity)
Samaritan Hospital of Brooklyn
St. Catherine's Hospital (materials partly written in German)
St. Martha's Sanitarium and Dispensary
St. Mary's General Hospital
St. Peter's Hospital
State University of New York Downstate Medical Center
Triboro Hospital
U.S. Base Hospital No. 37, A.E.F. (a unit of the Kings County Hospital that was active during World War I)
Women and Children's Hospitals:
House of St. Giles the Cripple
Memorial Hospital for Women and Children
St. Charles Hospital (also known as the Brooklyn Home for Blind, Crippled, and Defective Children)
St. Christopher's Hospital for Babies
Salvation Army Brooklyn Nursery and Infants' Hospital
Denominational and Ethnic Hospitals and Dispensaries:
German Hospital Society (materials mostly in German)
Jewish Hospital of Brooklyn
Lutheran Hospital Association of the City of New York and Vicinity (materials mostly in German)
Maimonides Hospital of Brooklyn (Jewish)
Swedish Hospital
Specialized Hospitals and Dispensaries:
Brooklyn Diet Dispensary
Central Throat Hospital and Polyclinic Dispensary
Long Island Throat and Lung Hospital and People's Dispensary Association
Mental Institutions:
Kings County Lunatic Asylum
Terminal Care Facilities:
Faith Home for Incurables
Rehabilitation Centers:
Inebriates' Home for Kings County
Homeopathic Hospitals and Dispensaries:
Brooklyn Eastern District Homeopathic Dispensary
Brooklyn Homeopathic Dispensary
Brooklyn Homeopathic Hospital
Brooklyn Homeopathic Lying-In Asylum (also represented under its subsequent names, including the Brooklyn Homeopathic Maternity; the Brooklyn Maternity; the Prospect Heights Hospital and Brooklyn Maternity; and the Prospect Heights Hospital)
Central Homeopathic Dispensary
Gates Avenue Homeopathic Dispensary
Medical Societies and Preventive Health Organizations:
Brooklyn Association for Mental Health
Brooklyn Temperance Society
Brooklyn Tuberculosis and Health Association (also represented under its subsequent names, including the Brooklyn Tuberculosis and Respiratory Disease Association and the Brooklyn Tuberculosis and Lung Association)
Committee on Prevention of Tuberculosis (a unit of the Brooklyn Bureau of Charities)
Homeopathic Medical Society of the County of Kings
Hospital Saturday and Sunday Association of the City of Brooklyn
Jeri Finesilver Cancer Foundation (affiliated with the Brookdale Hospital Medical Center)
Kings County Pharmaceutical Society
Sons of Temperance of North America's Grand Division of Eastern New York
Visiting Nurse Association of Brooklyn
Woman's Temperance Society of Brooklyn
Women's Health Protective Association of Brooklyn
Medical Colleges and Nurse Training Schools:
Associated Alumnae of Brooklyn Training Schools for Nurses (an organization comprised of alumnae from Brooklyn's several nurse training schools)
Brooklyn Homeopathic Hospital Training School for Nurses
Medical College of the State University of New York Downstate Medical Center
Memorial Hospital for Women and Children Training School for Nurses
New York State School for Training Nurses (also represented under its subsequent names, the New York State School for Nurses and the Prospect Heights Hospital School of Nursing)
Membership lists; Rules of procedure; Medical care |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Progress reports; Newsletters; Yearbooks; Terminal care facilities |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Medical colleges |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Nursing schools |x Alumni and alumnae |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Nursing schools |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Medicine |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Societies, etc.; Maternity homes |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Maternal health services |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Psychiatric hospitals |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Mental health services -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Catalogs; Bulletins; Manuals (instructional materials); Dispensaries |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Specialty hospitals |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Medicine |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Hospitals |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bylaws (administrative records); Annual reports; Constitutions; Women |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Societies and clubs; Health; Preventive health services |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Infant health services |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Temperance |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Temperance |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Societies, etc.; Tuberculosis |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Tuberculosis |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Prevention; Alcoholics |x Rehabilitation |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brochures; Charities, Medical |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Alcoholics |x Care |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Charity organization |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Child health services |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Church charities |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Children |x Institutional care |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Associated Alumnae of Brooklyn Training Schools for Nurses (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Bedford Dispensary (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Bedford Dispensary and Hospital (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Bedford Dispensary Association (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Bethany Deaconess Hospital Society; Brooklyn Central Dispensary (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn City Dispensary. Social Service Committee; Brooklyn Diet Dispensary; Brooklyn Eastern District Homeopathic Dispensary (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Eclectic Dispensary (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Homeopathic Dispensary (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn State Hospital; Brooklyn Temperance Society; Brooklyn Tuberculosis and Respiratory Disease Association (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Bushwick Hospital (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Central Homeopathic Dispensary (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Central Throat Hospital and Polyclinic Dispensary (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Downstate Medical Center (N.Y.); Gates Avenue Homeopathic Dispensary; German Hospital Society (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Homeopathic Medical Society of Kings County; House of St. Giles the Cripple; Inebriates' Home for Kings County; Jewish Hospital of Brooklyn; Kings County Lunatic Asylum (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Kings County Pharmaceutical Society; Long Island State Hospital; Long Island Throat and Lung Hospital and People's Dispensary Association (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Lutheran Hospital Association of the City of New York and Vicinity (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Maimonides Hospital of Brooklyn; Memorial Hospital for Women and Children (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Memorial Hospital for Women and Children (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.). Memorial Dispensary; Memorial Hospital for Women and Children (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.). Memorial Training School for Nurses; People's Medical and Surgical Dispensary (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Samaritan Hospital of Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Swedish Hospital (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); United States. Army. Base Hospital No. 37; Brooklyn Homeopathic Hospital; Brooklyn Homeopathic Hospital and Training School for Nurses; Brooklyn Homeopathic Lying-In Asylum (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Maternity (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Salvation Army. Brooklyn Nursery and Infants' Hospital; St. Christopher's Hospital for Babies; Brooklyn Tuberculosis and Health Association; Brooklyn Bureau of Charities. Committee on Prevention of Tuberculosis; Brooklyn Association for Mental Health (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Faith Home for Incurables (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Sons of Temperance of North America. Grand Division of Eastern New York; Woman's Temperance Society of Brooklyn, N.Y.; Women's Health Protective Association of Brooklyn (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Home for Blind, Crippled, and Defective Children (Port Jefferson, N.Y.); Prospect Heights Hospital and Brooklyn Maternity (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); St. Peter's Hospital (Cobble Hill, New York, N.Y.); Brookdale Hospital Medical Center (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Prospect Heights Hospital (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.). School of Nursing. Alumnae Association; Jeri Finesilver Cancer Foundation (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); St. Mary's Hospital (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); St. Martha's Sanitarium and Dispensary (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); St. Catharine's Hospital (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); St. Mary's General Hospital (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Triboro Hospital (Queens, New York, N.Y.); Visiting Nurse Association of Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); St. Charles Hospital (Port Jefferson, N.Y.); Downstate Medical Center (N.Y.). Alumni Association; Brooklyn Hospital Saturday and Sunday Association; Brooklyn Homeopathic Maternity (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
- Associated Alumnae of Brooklyn Training Schools for Nurses, 1897 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Historical note
  An organization comprised of alumnae from Brooklyn's several nurse training schools.
- Bedford Dispensary Association, 1889, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Also known as the Bedford Dispensary and Hospital and the Bedford Dispensary.
- Bedford Dispensary, 1893-1894 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Also known as the Bedford Dispensary and Hospital and the Bedford Dispensary Association.
- Bedford Dispensary and Hospital, 1895-1903 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Also known as the Bedford Dispensary Association and the Bedford Dispensary.
- Bethany Deaconess (and) Hospital (Society), 1926-1956 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Brooklyn Association for Mental Health, 1960-1972 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Brooklyn Central Dispensary, 1889-1892 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Brooklyn City Dispensary, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Brooklyn Committee on Prevention of Tuberculosis, 1909-1911 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  A unit of the Brooklyn Bureau of Charities.
- Brooklyn Diet Dispensary, 1879-1908 (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
- Brooklyn Eastern District Homeopathic Dispensary, 1892, 1894 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Brooklyn Eclectic Dispensary, 1895-1897 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Brooklyn Homeopathic Dispensary, 1869-1870 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Brooklyn Homeopathic Hospital, 1874-1889 (Box 2, Folder 3-4)
  Scope and Contents
  Reports and by-laws. Later reports also cover the hospital's training school for nurses.
- Brooklyn Homeopathic Lying-In Asylum, 1871 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  Later Brooklyn Homeopathic Maternity and then Prospect Heights Hospital and Brooklyn Maternity.
- Brooklyn Homeopathic Maternity, 1871-1900 (Box 7)
  Later Prospect Heights Hospital and Brooklyn Maternity.
- Brooklyn Hospital Saturday and Sunday Association, 1882-1932 (Box 2, Folder 6, Box 7)
- Brooklyn Nursery and Infants' Hospital, 1872-1914 (Box 6, Folder 8-10)
  Originally called The Brooklyn Nursery.
- Brooklyn State Hospital, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  Originally the Long Island State Hospital.
- Brooklyn Temperance Society, 1829 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Brooklyn Tuberculosis and Health Association, 1928-1929, 1962-1963, 1965-1967 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  Later known as the Brooklyn Tuberculosis and Respiratory Disease Association.
- Brooklyn Tuberculosis and Respiratory Disease Association, 1973-1975 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  Biographical / Historical
  Originally known as the Brooklyn Tuberculosis and Health Association.
- Bushwick Hospital, 1911-1912 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Central Homeopathic Dispensary, 1884-1897 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Central Throat Hospital and Polyclinic Dispensary, 1894 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Faith Home for Incurables, 1885-1915 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Gates Avenue Homeopathic Dispensary, 1879 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- German Hospital Society, 1897, 1911-1914 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Homeopathic Medical Society of the County of Kings, 1870, 1881, 1890 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- House of St. Giles the Cripple, 1892-1939 (Box 3, Folder 3-6)
  Reports, newsletters, and yearbooks (1910-1939).
- Inebriates' Home for Kings County, 1868-1885 (Box 3, Folder 7, Box 4, Folder 1)
- Jeri Finesilver Cancer Foundation, circa 1948 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  Affiliated with the Brookdale Hospital Medical Center.
- Jewish Hospital of Brooklyn, 1907-1908 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Kings County Lunatic Asylum, 1861-1870 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Kings County Pharmaceutical Society, 1888 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Long Island State Hospital, 1912-1916 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  Later the Brooklyn State Hospital.
- Long Island Throat and Lung Hospital and People's Dispensary Association, 1892-1893 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Lutheran Hospital Association of the City of New York and Vicinity, 1895-1897 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Maimonides Hospital of Brooklyn, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Memorial Hospital for Women and Children, 1891-1899 (Box 4, Folder 10-11)
  Annual reports and Tablet magazine.
- Memorial Hospital for Women and Children Training School for Nurses, 1896-1897 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Prospect Heights Hospital and Brooklyn Maternity, 1901-1922 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  Originally Brooklyn Homeopathic Lying-In Asylum and then Brooklyn Homeopathic Maternity.
- Prospect Heights Hospital School of Nursing, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- People's Medical and Surgical Dispensary, 1890 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- St. Catharine's Hospital, 1877-1896 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- St. Charles Hospital, 1928-1932 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  Also known as the Brooklyn Home for Blind, Crippled, and Defective Children.
- St. Christopher's Hospital for Babies, 1897-1922 (Box 5, Folder 6, Box 8)
- St. Martha's Sanitarium and Dispensary, 1893-1896 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- St. Mary's General Hospital, 1882, 1889, 1908 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- St. Peter's Hospital, 1877, 1884, 1889-1896, 1899 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Salvation Army Brooklyn Nursery and Infants' Hospital, 1927 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Samaritan Hospital of Brooklyn, 1907-1914, 1925, 1962-1963 (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Sons of Temperance of North America's Grand Division of Eastern New York, 1868 (Box 5, Folder 12)
- SUNY (State University of New York) Downstate Medical Center, 1958-1973 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Swedish Hospital, circa mid-20th century (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Triboro Hospital, 1946-1948 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- U.S. Base Hospital No. 37, A.E.F., 1951-1955 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  A unit of the Kings County Hospital that was active during World War I (WWI).
- Visiting Nurse Association of Brooklyn, 1974-1997 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  Newsletters 1974-1997 and 1989 annual report.
- Woman's Temperance Society of Brooklyn, 1874 (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Women's Health Protective Association of Brooklyn, 1894 (Box 6, Folder 7)